the main reason
why the Buddha would say
if he wanted to describe the
worst type of suffering he would say
like Pains of dying death or those who
dying not because it's physically unpleasant
not because it's physically unpleasant
that's not why those planes are there
it's the mental anguish
so what's the
what's the main characteristic
of the
discomfort of death or thoughts of dying
what's that the most unpleasant aspect
of it
how can you describe it
not control how is that manifested
like when you don't have control at all
it threatens Your Existence yeah it
threatens yourself your sense you're as
in as yeah so which kind of what example
would then can you experience in the
world
um that would resemble that ultimate
threat to death
while you're still alive
that would partake in exactly insane
nature
sorry sickness uh yeah all of this all
of these things they all have this one
threading imprisonment yeah no
imprisonment what's the the main the main
what's the the main the main
characteristic of imprisonment is
confinement Okay so generally confinement is the
Okay so generally confinement is the
worst you know you can have it
a little bit more so but the worst
possible idea the worst phobias are the
ideas of when you confined you can't
move you can't breathe you can't do
anything so confined within your own
body and you can get the glimpses of that
and you can get the glimpses of that
throughout
life on account of this so that but
usually the view will kind of keep it
pinned to the life and circumstances
failing to understand that the
possibility of confinement will
ultimately be exemplified for you
through the experience of death or those
of dying
and that's exactly why the Buddha would
described it so the reason why death and
those who dying pains as like those of
dying is so unpleasant it's because of
the confinement that the Mind naturally
resists craves against not because it's
unpleasant in and of itself
it might be this uncomfortable but the
mental language does not come
automatically with it that is the mental
language of the mind that it's now
facing its confinement
and that's the worst fear and that's the
worst pain so if the Mind learns how not
to move amidst confinement and
everything these examples are
confinements then eventually even death
will not be able to move it because it's
exactly the same thing you're confined
within your own senses
they belong tomorrow eyes sights ears
nose everything
but it's a confinement that you don't
see because well it's confining in this
prison but look all the joys and
Pleasures they get I was like well yeah
but because of those Joys you are
confined not other way around
and once you start seeing that then you
realize okay these are just baits that
keep me confined in this environment
to every suffering that you have is that
you're not getting what you want you're
confined there's a limit to what you can
get yeah but yourself wants to
appropriate confinement I'm not getting
what I no I'm getting what I don't want
I'm crushed in yeah so that's why I kept
crushed in yeah so that's why I kept
saying in the past as well like if a
person wants to contemplate death you
don't contemplating in these abstract
terms or impersonal looking at the dead
bodies and so on or just find things
that can find you
uh called sense restraint you will be
confining saying no to your desires will
be very confining
doing things you don't want to do in
terms of Duties will be very confining
uh do that and see whether your mind
moves or not and how much and that's
your training not not allow your mind to
move amidst things they want to move you and
amidst things they want to move you and
that's the that eventually can result in
that opening within the confinement not
left right below or or above it
so while fully confined the mind is
released from it turned away from it
from it turned away from it
dispatch through this passion no other
way there's no other way there's not a
there's no other way there's not a
mystical
portal that you can access through this
is through share this passion amidst the
confinement and discomfortable
confinement if you have wisdom
if you have wisdom
patience that confinement can be
gradually built up so you would not
necessarily suffer so sharply
immediately for a long time
but either way sometimes you just have
to
like it's not up to you to decide
as the Buddha said for somebody the the
the path towards that opening that
freedom is gonna it's gonna be quick and
is gonna it's gonna be quick and
unpleasant
quick and pleasant slow and pleasant and
slow and unpleasant
but you'll only yeah you will know that
only in hindsight which way it was and
again I think if we were to bet on which
way most people would be two and a half
Millennia after the Buddha
probably it's going to be slowing up
unpleasant for more store for most of
most mostly everyone yeah
but again even that displeasure does not
mean it's going to be this excruciating
torment by default automatically no that
is determined by how much you actively
crave against it
it's not like a pool of pain that you
have to sort of drain and just just
endure through
no it's it's you could technically
abandon it right there and then
if you if you're able to to face it for
what it is
uh keep in mind this passionately
towards it and do that endurance that we
talk about
in regard to that phenomenon of
confinement then everything else will just fall away
it's that's what Tuka is I can't find
yeah no getting what you want being
separated from what you what you want
being united what you don't want
whether you want it or not yeah okay
yeah having there being a body they're
being experienced well exactly like once
you start looking at it closely birth or
authentically you recognize your own
eyes nose senses
you had no saying they're Rising you
certainly had no say in what they want
in their desires
you just fully and perpetually
subjected to it pressure by it confined
by it
confined by the duty of maintaining and
feeding your desires otherwise the mind
will just become too unbearable
and yeah that's that's like a hard labor
prison camp
you also have to work all the time
so recognizing your confinement the
extent of confinement that you you are
in hmm
you're seeing understanding Tuka
feeling it
but yeah I think pretty much yeah yeah I
did but you actually have to recognizing
then what brings that duka you realize
well it's not the confinement
so it's like that you recognize the duka
but it's not the Duke you recognize the
duka then you recognize the source then
you recognize the escape from duka
and the source is
your
fighting inside that or fighting against
resisting resisting confinement
by default at face value
so for as long as you have the view or
views that oh you know there's some
pleasant experience that I'm pressured
by confined by
scores because of such and such thing
happened that's already
view that looks past the confinement
blames even something else
so first you just have to stop
acting out of those views
you might think I suffer because he said
something that upset me but because I
restrain I don't feel their View and
then their view actually falls away and
I realize well I suffer because
suffering Arisen that's it
yes they said something another day
somebody else didn't do such it's always
something that's going to be seemingly
the reason at the face value but
fundamentally I Suffolk who suffering is
present I suffer because I resist confinement
I suffer because I resist confinement
that's it
presence of resistance
means suffering absence of resistance
means not suffering amidst confinement
and that's exactly what to describe
those who understand this they don't
suffer amidst the suffering
so the extent of confinement
reveals the extent of dukkha because it
shows the extent of your resistance
towards it so that's the first well the
Four Noble Truths
so then how do you tame your mind to
remove any trace of resistance
within confinement whether it's a
confinement of Desire
pressure to act out
any other type of confinement how do you
train your mind well that's the nobility
path you realize okay so it's not I
can't decide if I will to tell this mind
to stop resisting it
kicking and screaming like a wild animal
but if I adhere to certain behaviors
avoid certain other behaviors cultivate
skillful things avoid unskillful things
eat suitable food not unsuitable food
damn my senses
that animal will have to calm down and
when that animal comes down my view will
be fulfilled view of freedom and it's
confinement that I understood
and that's like Sultan's understanding
that can then lead to Argent if he fully
tames that mind within what he already
understood